A Finding Aid to the Henry Botkin papers, circa 1927-1982, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Henry Botkin papers
circa 1927-1982
Archives of American Art
Botkin, Henry, 1896-1983
AAA.botkhenr
Archival Resource Key
3 Linear feet
The papers of painter Henry Botkin measure 3 linear feet, date from circa 1927-1982, and illustrate his career through biographical material, correspondence, writings, personal business records, printed and photographic material, and artwork.
Biographical / Historical
Henry Botkin (1896-1983) was a painter who worked primarily in New York. He was born in Boston, Massachusetts and trained at both the Massachusetts School of Art and the Art Students League before moving to New York City. While in New York, Botkin worked as an illustrator for Harper's, The Saturday Evening Post, and Century magazine. In the early 1920s he moved to Paris to begin exploring Impressionism as a painting style. Botkin is known for painting the theater, still lifes, and landscapes. He is also known for his paintings of Black people in the South Carolina low country which have faced criticism about their lack of social realism. Botkin returned to New York in 1930, married his wife Rhoda Lehman, and in 1934 became an art agent to his cousin art collector George Gershwin and others.
In the late 1930s, Botkin switched to the abstract painting style in oils, and took an active role in bringing the style to public attention. He became part of the Artist's Equity Association, The American Abstract Artists Group 256 in Provincetown, and the Federation of Modern Painters and Sculptors where he served as president from 1957-1961.
In 1955, Botkin put together the first exhibition of American abstract art at the Museum of Modern Art in Tokyo, Japan and organized the sale of five hundred and forty paintings at the Whitney Museum in New York in 1959. Botkin participated in various public events and programs and taught privately in New York, California, and Provincetown, Massachusetts. In the early 1950s Botkin began working with collages which became his main art form until his death. Botkin died in 1983 at the age of eigthy-seven in New York City.
Arrangement
This collection consists of seven series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1945-1972 (.1 Linear feet: Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1928-1979 (.2 Linear feet: Box 1)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1936-1977 (.3 Linear feet: Box 1)
Series 4: Personal Business Records, circa 1927-1977 (.6 Linear feet: Boxes 1-2)
Series 5: Printed Material, circa 1927-1982 (.8 Linear feet: Box 2)
Series 6: Photographic Material, circa 1928-1977 (.9 Linear feet: Boxes 3-5)
Series 7: Artwork, circa 1965-1967 (.1 Linear feet: Box 5)
Scope and Contents
The Henry Botkin papers measure 3 linear feet and date from circa 1927-1982. Biographical materials include multiple interviews with Botkin, one of which is for the Today Show, membership cards for the Audubon Artists and Artists Equity Association, and Botkin's resume. Correspondence is with George Gershwin, Syracuse University, and others. Writings include autobiographical writings, lectures and speeches by Botkin, artwork reviews of Botkin's art, and miscellaneous writings by others. Personal business records consist of materials regarding various professional organizations, materials on Judy Cimaglia, materials on Botkin's daughter Toinette (Botkin) Laurent, and other business records. Printed material includes exhibition announcements and catalogs, press releases, and picture postcards. Photographic material consists of photographs of Botkin, his wife Rhoda Lehman, friends and family, and various exhibitions. Artwork includes pieces by Botkin and others.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Researchers interested in accessing born-digital records or audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Papers were lent for microfilming from 1969 to 1982 by Henry Botkin, his son Glenn Botkin, and his assistant Rene Barilleaux.
Related Materials
Henry Botkin papers also held at Syracuse University.
Separated Materials
The Archives of American Art also holds microfilm of material lent for microfilming (reels D388, N69-67, N69-68, N69-91, N70-25, N70-68, 2895-2897, and 4314) including biographical material, letters, notes, writings, business records, artworks, scrapbook pages, printed material, and photographs, from 1969-1982. Loaned materials were returned to the lender and are not described in the collection container inventory.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the collection and material lent for microfilming are available on 35mm microfilm reels D388, N69-67, N69-68, N69-91, N70-25, N70-68, 2895-2897, and 4314 at the Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Drawings; Scrapbooks; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Painters -- Massachusetts -- Provincetown; Sound recordings; Interviews; Artists Equity Association; Federation of Modern Painters and Sculptors; Gallery 256 (Provincetown, Mass.)
- Biographical Material, circa 1945-1972; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; .1 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical material includes multiple interviews with Henry Botkin, membership cards for the Audubon Artists and Artists Equity Association, Botkin's resume, and a booklet of telephone numbers.
  - Resume, circa 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Interviews, Archival Resource Key
    - "Henry Botkin", circa 1970; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel 1/4" reel (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Meet the Artist", Interview by Colette Roberts, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette; 1 Sound tape reel 1/4" reel (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Monologue", by Henry Botkin, 1970, Oct. 11; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel 1/4" reel; 1 Sound cassette (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Today Show", Interview with Henry Botkin, 1963, June 4; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette; 1 Sound tape reel 1/4" reel (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - United States Treasury Department, Certificate for Service in the Seventh War Loan Project, circa 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Who's Who in American Art, Biographical Information Form, circa 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Organization Membership Cards, circa 1949-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Booklet of Telephone Numbers, circa 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, circa 1928-1979; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; .2 Linear feet Box 1
  Correspondence is with George Gershwin, Syracuse University regarding Botkin's papers and exhibitions, and others.
  - Correspondence (1920s), circa 1928; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence (1930s), circa 1930-1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence (1940s), circa 1941-1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence (1950s), circa 1950-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - Correspondence (1960s), circa 1961-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15-17)
  - Correspondence (1970s), circa 1970-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Gershwin, George, circa 1931-1933; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Syracuse University, circa 1965-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Writings, circa 1936-1977; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; .3 Linear feet Box 1
  Writings include autobiographical writings, lectures and speeches, and notebooks, as well as reviews of Botkin's artwork and miscellaneous writings by others.
  - By Botkin, Archival Resource Key
    - Thoughts on My Life and Career, circa 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Autobiographical Writings, circa 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Research Proposal, circa 1936-1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Lectures, circa 1969-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Rough Drafts, circa 1965-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Speeches, circa 1965-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Notebooks, circa 1952-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27-28)
    - Miscellaneous Notes, circa 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Miscellaneous Writings, circa 1969-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - By Others, Archival Resource Key
    - List of Botkin's Acquaintances, circa 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Reviews of Artwork, circa 1960-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Miscellaneous Writings, circa 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Personal Business Records, circa 1927-1977; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; .6 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Personal business records include materials regarding various professional organizations, materials on Judy Cimaglia, materials on Botkin's daughter Toinette (Botkin) Laurent, a gallery floor plan, and miscellaneous business records.
  - American Abstract Artists, circa 1949-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - American Institute of Graphic Artists, Lease Agreement, 1952, Jan 28; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Artists Equity Association, circa 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36-42)
  - Artists For Victory, circa 1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Art Students League of New York, circa 1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Associated American Artists, circa 1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Cimaglia, Judy, circa 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Federation of Modern Painters and Sculptors, circa 1957-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Laurent, Toinette, circa 1961-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Overseas Museum Project", Final Report, circa 1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Advertisement Purchase Receipts, circa 1927-1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Artwork Sales Records, circa 1947-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Bills and Receipts for Art Supplies, circa 1937-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  - Gallery Floor Plan, circa 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Price Lists, circa 1963-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Business Records, circa 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Printed Material, circa 1927-1982; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; .8 Linear feet Box 2
  Printed material includes exhibition announcements and catalogs, materials regarding George Gershwin, press releases, and picture postcards from various locations.
  - Exhibition Announcements, circa 1927-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15-22)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, circa 1927-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23-30)
  - Gershwin, George, circa 1931-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Art Publications, circa 1951-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - News Clippings, circa 1929-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 33-37)
  - News Clippings, Scrapbook, circa 1927-1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 38-40)
  - Picture Postcards, Archival Resource Key
    - Mexico, circa 1964-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Provincetown, circa 1964-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Works of Art, circa 1964-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Miscellaneous Postcards, circa 1964-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Press Releases, circa 1959-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, circa 1946-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Photographic Material, circa 1928-1977; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; .9 Linear feet Boxes 3-5
  Photographic material includes photographs of Henry Botkin, Rhoda Lehman, George Gershwin, family and friends, artwork, and various museums and exhibitions.
  - Botkin, Henry, circa 1932-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Gershwin, George, circa 1945-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Lehman, Rhoda, circa 1932-1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Family and Friends, circa 1937-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
  - Art Related Events, circa 1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Art Students League, circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Botkin's Studio, circa 1928-1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
  - Buildings, circa 1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Exhibitions, circa 1939-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12-15)
  - Gallery Events, circa 1952-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Provincetown (1955), Exhibition, circa 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Rehn Gallery (1977), Exhibition, circa 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Riverside Museum, circa 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Syracuse University (1971), Exhibition, circa 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Donated to Artists Equity Sale at Whitney Museum, circa 1943-1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1928-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2-12)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1928-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1-5)
- Artwork, circa 1965-1967; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; .1 Linear feet Box 5
  Artwork includes a sketch and collage by Botkin and drawings, paintings, and sketches by others.
  - Artwork by Botkin, circa 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Artwork by Others, circa 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 7)